A Guide to the Margaretta (Happy) Fitler Rockefeller papers, Art Files FA1716
Rockefeller Archive Center
Margaretta (Happy) Fitler Rockefeller papers, Art Files
1974-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Margaretta Fitler
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Altman, Cynthia, Curator
Uht, Carol Kinzel
FA1716
3.40 Cubic Feet 7 card file boxes (4 x 6) and 5 letter document boxes
Scope and Contents
The art files of Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller document the works of art originally collected by her husband, Nelson A. Rockefeller, and inherited by Happy after his death in 1979. These files are a combination of records on the acquisition, maintenance, display, loan, and (in some cases) disposition of the artworks. The most significant type of record in this collection is the cohort of art index cards that were created as a catalog of each object or set of objects. They originate from the early 1940s through the 1990s, although the vast bulk predate Governor Rockefeller's death. They were originally incorporated within the set of index cards that are found in the Nelson A. Rockefeller Art Files in FA340. Used as a tool for tracking the collection, the cards were updated either in type or handwriting as the disposition of a piece changed—through sale, gift, or other removal from the collection.
Carol K. Uht and later Cynthia B. Altman were the Rockefellers' curators. They created the cards to record vital information about each artwork for quick access: artist, title, medium, year of creation, dimensions, source of acquisition, year of acquisition, and usually the price paid.
The cards are grouped by cataloguing number, which denotes categories of fine art and objects. The categories include modern art, nonmodern art (which is further broken down by country or region of origin), porcelain, silver, furniture, and decorative art. Each object or set of objects has a two-part number, the first of which refers to the category while the second is a unique identifier. For example, #25-588 is item number 588 of the modern art pieces. Likewise, #11-234 is item number 234 of the nonmodern pieces from Japan. This collection also includes negatives of both modern and nonmodern pieces, usually organized in the same manner as the card index. Other records in the collection are sparse and only refer to selected individual works, typically ones that were lent or sold. These files contain inventories, appraisals, insurance valuations, catalogues, loan requests, and some correspondence. Please note that the documentation is not comprehensive in that only a handful of works of art are discussed. Lastly, the collections ends with general content related to properties owned by Happy Rockefeller.
Art, Modern; Indigenous art; Folk art
- Art Reference Index Cards, Sections 1 through 9: Primitive and Folk Art Overview of Sections (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 1: Primitive and Folk Art, South America 1-1 to 1-49 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 1: Primitive and Folk Art, South America 1-50 to 1-99 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 1: Primitive and Folk Art, South America 1-100 to 1-128 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-1 to 2-49 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-50 to 2-99 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-100 to 2-149 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-150 to 2-199 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-200 to 2-249 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 2: Primitive and Folk Art, Mexico and South America 2-250 to 2-406 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 3: Primitive and Folk Art, North American Indian 3-1 to 3-53 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 4: Primitive and Folk Art, Oceania 4-1 to 4-49 (Box 1)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 4: Primitive and Folk Art, Oceania 4-50 to 4-148 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 5: Primitive and Folk Art, Africa 5-1 to 5-49 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 5: Primitive and Folk Art, Africa 5-50 to 5-99 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 5: Primitive and Folk Art, Africa 5-100 to 5-175 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 6: Primitive and Folk Art, Early American 6-1 to 6-99 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 6: Primitive and Folk Art, Early American 6-100 to 6-146 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Sections 10 through 19: Far East and Middle East Art (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 10: Far East and Middle East Art, China 10-1 to 10-145 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-1 to 11-49 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-50 to 11-149 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-150 to 11-199 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-200 to 11-299 (Box 2)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-300 to 11-399 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 11: Far East and Middle East Art, Japan 11-400 to 11-645 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 12: Far East and Middle East Art, India and Burma, 12-1 to 12-21 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 13: Far East and Middle East Art, Siam, Korea, and Tibet, 13-1 to 13-35 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Sections 20 through 24: Europe and the Mediterranean Art (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 20: Europe and Mediterranean Art, Greece and Greek Culture 20-1 to 20-55 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 21: Europe and Mediterranean Art, Egypt 21-1 to 21-8 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 22: Europe and Mediterranean Art, Western Europe Pre-modern 22-1 to 22-148 (Box 3)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 23: Europe and Mediterranean Art, Near East 23-1 to 23-8 (Box 3)
- Negatives for Primitive and Folk Art, Sections 4 and 5: Oceania and Africa (Box 3)
- Negatives for Primitive and Folk Art, Section 6: American Folk Art (Box 3)
- Negatives for Primitive and Folk Art, Section 7: Early European (Box 3)
- Negatives for Far East Art, Section 10: China (Box 4)
- Negatives for Far East Art, Section 11: Japan (Box 4)
- Negatives for Far East Art, Sections 12 and 13: India and Burma; Siam, Korea, and Tibet (Box 4)
- Negatives for Europe and Mediterranean Art, Sections 20 to 23: Greece; Egypt; Western Europe Pre-modern; Near East (Box 4)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Section 25: Modern Art, A to Z (Box 5)
- Negatives for Modern Art, Section 25 (Box 5)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Porcelain (Box 6)
- Art Reference Index Cards, Silver (Box 6)
- Art Reference Index Cards for Cancelled Art to Mary Clark Rockefeller, 1961 (Box 7)
- Art Reference Index Cards for Cancelled Porcelain and Silver (Box 7)
- Art Reference Index Cards for Cancelled Art from the Estate of John D. Rockefeller Jr. (Box 7)
- Art Reference Index Cards for Cancelled Art from the Estate of Martha Baird Rockefeller and the Estate of Winthrop Rockefeller (Box 7)
- Art Reference Index Cards for General Cancelled Art: Modern Art and Porcelain (Box 7)
- Sales of Art: Asian Works of Art, 1997-1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Sales of Art: Chait Galleries, Asian Works of Art, 1988-1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Sales of Art: Iranian Sculpture, 2010-2011 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Sales of Art: Modern Works of Art, 1981-1997 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Sales of Art: Modern Works of Art, 1978-2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Sales of Art: Modern Works of Art, Glarner Prints, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Sales of Art: Furnishings, Decorative Pieces, 1979-1993 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Sales of Art: Furniture, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Sales of Art: Asian Works sold by Lally and Company, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Sales of Art: Cycladic Head (marble), 1976-1993 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Gift of Art: Kenneth Davies, Red Accent, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Gift of Art: Kiehart, copy of Liberman's Portrait of Nelson Rockefeller, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Gift of Art: Kiesler, Galaxy, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Gift of Art: Marini, Bust of Wallace K. Harrison, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Gift of Art: George II Chair, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Gifts of Art: Works Being Considered for Gifts, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Loans of Art: Blume, Excavation, 2013-2014 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Loans of Art: Gris, Study: Ship's Deck, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Loans of Art: Noguchi, Mr. One Man and Small Child, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Request to View Art: Jawlensky, Cottage in the Woods: 2009 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Rights and Reproduction Requests for Use of Images of Art: Various, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Rights and Reproduction Requests for Use of Images of Art: Various, 1992-1996 (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Rights and Reproduction Requests for Use of Images of Art: Fifth Avenue Apartment Living Room, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Conservation of Art: Various artwork, 1982-2012 (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Conservation of Art: Authenticity Test: T'ang Polo Player, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 25)
- Acquisitions of Art: Decorative Reproductions (NRC Inc.), likely for gifts, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  Scope and Contents
  Possibile options for gifts, from the Nelson Rockefeller Collection Inc.--an art reproduction company.
- Sale of Boat: Bertram "Sea Lady", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 27)
- Nelson Rockefeller's Modern Art Book, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 28)
- Sotheby Parke Bernet appraisal: Annotated Kykuit appraisal, 1979 October (Box 9, Folder 29)
- Sotheby Parke Bernet appraisal: Pocantico Guest House, 1979 September (Box 9, Folder 30)
  Also known as Hawes Guest House or Harrison Guest House (designed by Wallace Harrison).
- Sotheby Parke Bernet appraisal: The Anchorage, Seal Harbor, Maine, 1979 September (Box 9, Folder 31)
- Sotheby Parke Bernet appraisal: 22 West 55th Street, Manhattan, 1979 September (Box 9, Folder 32)
- Sotheby Parke Bernet appraisal: 13 West 54th Street, Manhattan, 1979 September (Box 9, Folder 33)
- Sotheby's appraisal: Japanese House (1 of 2), 1992 June (Box 10, Folder 34)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted - Living Rockefeller family - Restricted for Life
- Sotheby's appraisal: Japanese House (2 of 2), 1992 June (Box 10, Folder 35)
- Sotheby's appraisal: Japanese House, 1992 June (Box 10, Folder 36)
- Sotheby's appraisal: "Additional Property", 1982 May (Box 10, Folder 37)
  This small appraisal was included in the second copy of the main Japanese House appraisal from 1992, even though this valuation of pieces of metal, procelain, and pottery was completed in 1982 as an addendum to the original 1979 appraisal of the NAR estate.
- Sotheby's appraisal: Teahouse contents, 1992 August (Box 10, Folder 38)
- Sotheby's appraisal: Pocantico Hills Guest House, 1992 June (Box 10, Folder 39)
  Likely the contents of the property also known as Hawes Guest House and Harrison House (designed by Wallace Harrison).
- Sotheby's appraisal: 812 Fifth Avenue, Manhattan, 2001 December (Box 10, Folder 40)
- Christie's appraisal and sales proposal: Picasso tapestry after Guernica, 2010 February (Box 10, Folder 41)
  Curator Cynthia Altman requested a valuation be done by Christie's of this Picasso tapestry. Christie's produced a sales proposal to put the work up for auction.
- Sotheyby's appraisal: All New York properties, 2007 April (Box 11, Folder 42)
  The appraisal includes 812 Fifth Avenue in Manhattan and the following in Pocantico Hills: Japanese House, Havenwood House, Pool House, Tea House, and Kykuit Main House (fine art only).
- Sotheyby's appraisal: All New York properties, 2007 June (Box 11, Folder 43)
- Art and Tangible Property: Malinda F. Menotti, 1981-1987 (Box 11, Folder 44)
- Properties: Pocantico Hills: Kurt Kappmeyer responsibilities, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 45)
  Restricted - Personnnel - Open in 2064
- Properties: Pocantico Hills: Nelson A. Rockefeller Jr. property, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 46)
- Properties: Pocantico Hills: Dennis Dwyer copies of ownership and agreements, 1985; 1993 (Box 11, Folder 47)
- Properties: Pocantico Hills: Hawes House (currently, Havenwood), 1986-1990 (Box 12, Folder 48)
- Properties: Manhattan: 812 Fifth Avenue, art and windows, 1983-1992 (Box 12, Folder 49)
- Colonial Williamsburg: Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Center exhibit, 1991-1992 (Box 12, Folder 50)
  Loan of work of art.